Guide to the Kevin Coffee Papers TAM.328
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kevin Coffee Papers
1978-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Coffee, Kevin
TAM.328
3.92 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes, 1 small box, and 1 folder in a shared flat box
3 Betamax
3 VHS
15 audiocassettes
Established in 1984, No Business As Usual (NBAU) was an anti-war initiative comprised of various activist groups. It was begun to organize public opposition and protest to the United States government's military spending, planning, and anticipated use of nuclear weapons against the USSR. Kevin Coffee is an archaeologist and museologist whose research focuses on urbanization and industrialization. He taught at Columbia College Chicago from 1982-1988. He became the faculty sponsor for an anti-war student group in 1983, and in 1989, the NBAU clearinghouse files were transferred to his care. The Kevin Coffee Papers (1978-1991) are comprised of materials created and collected by the No Business as Usual network and Coffee in his role as faculty advisor for the NBAU student chapter at Columbia College Chicago. Materials include national mailings from the San Francisco clearinghouse, correspondence, press clippings, press releases and statements, action (event) flyers and photographs, and audio and video recordings of various NBAU sponsored events.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kevin Coffee in 2005. The accession number associated with this gift is 2005.019.
Historical Note
Established in 1984, No Business As Usual (NBAU) was an anti-war initiative comprised of various activist groups. It was begun to organize public opposition and protest to the United States government's military spending, planning, and anticipated use of nuclear weapons against the USSR. Its initial focus was to coordinate a national day of protest on April 29, 1985. A range of progressive voices, including C. Clark Kissinger and Leonard Post, were involved in the creation of the NBAU project. They formed an ad-hoc coordinating committee to faciliate communication about organizing events. On April 29, 1985, small and large protests were staged in cities and towns and on college campuses across the United States. Volunteers maintained a national mailing list and communication network through a clearinghouse mail drop in San Francisco. Following the success of April 29, 1985, the No Business As Usual Action network formed in order for activists to maintain contact and attempt further joint activities. The NBAU network persisted in calling attention to war planning and preparation, which included promoting the pledge by more than 6,500 university research scientists to refuse to participate in weapons research. During this same time, some NBAU-affiliated groups continued to focus their attention on military interventions by the United States in Central America, especially Nicaragua, and the Iran-Iraq War. In 1989, the volunteers in San Francisco determined that they could no longer provide support for the clearinghouse, so volunteers in New York agreed to coordinate communications among activists. By mid-1991, the anti-world war focus of the network had been eclipsed by world and national events.
Source Cited:
Coffee, Kevin. "No Business as Usual Network/No Business as Usual Action Network Description." April 22, 2025
Biographical Note
Kevin Coffee is an archaeologist and museologist whose research focuses on urbanization and industrialization. He taught at Columbia College Chicago from 1982-1988. He became the faculty sponsor for an anti-war student group in 1983, and many of the students formed a No Business as Usual group on campus. Coffee participated in NBAU events and collaborated with colleagues on other social justice public events. In 1987, Coffee moved to New York to work at the American Museum of Natural History. In 1989, the NBAU clearinghouse files were transferred to his care. From 2018-2023, Coffee worked as the chief interpretation and education officer at Lowell National Historical Park in Lowell, Massachusetts.
Arrangement
Arranged alphanumerically.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Appraisal
One off-air recording of a copyrighted broadcast, in analog format, has been appraised out of the collection due to copyright limitations.
Scope and Contents
The Kevin Coffee Papers (1978-1991) are comprised of materials created and collected by the No Business as Usual network and Coffee in his role as faculty advisor for the NBAU student chapter at Columbia College Chicago. Materials include national mailings from the San Francisco clearinghouse, correspondence, press clippings, press releases and statements, action (event) flyers and photographs, and audio and video recordings of various NBAU sponsored events. Also included are mailings, flyers, and photographs from different local chapters, mainly in Chicago, Boston, and New York. A large part of the collection contains printed matter, such as newsletters and mailings, from other organizations. Organizations include the American Service Friends Committee, Mobilization for Survival, and the War Resisters League. All of the materials in the collection reflect the main mission of NBAU, which was to bring attention to the government's war efforts, protest the use of nuclear weapons, and disrupt any developments that would lead to World War III.
Anti-war demonstrations.; Nuclear disarmament.; Protest movements.; Political activists.; Activists -- United States -- 1980-2011; Peace movements; Coffee, Kevin; Kissinger, Charles C. (Charles Clark)
- Actions -- A Call to Act, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Actions -- No Business as Usual Day, April 1985
  - Flyers and Press Clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Posters (Box Shared Tamiment 198, Folder 4)
- Actions -- Armed Forces Day Protest, May 1985
  - Fliers and Photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Video Recording -- "Tanks a Million" (Box 8, Betamax 328.0003)
- Actions -- Hiroshima/Nagasaki Anniversary Protests, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Actions -- Star Wars Contracts Packet, October 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Actions -- Pre-War Summit Forum -- New York, November 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Actions -- Star Wars Educational, March 1986
  - Audio Recording -- Kissinger-Hutchinson -- Tape 1 (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.0008)
  - Audio Recording -- Kissinger-Hutchinson -- Tape 2 (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.001)
- Actions -- National Day of Action, April 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Actions -- Protests Againts the Bombing of Libya, April-May 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Actions -- No Business as Usual Focus Star Wars!, October 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Actions -- Living in Prewar America Symposium -- New York, October 1986
  - Posters (Box Shared Tamiment 198, Folder 4)
  - Programs and Flyers (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Actions -- Opposition to Miniseries Amerika, February 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Actions -- Student and Youth National Day of No Business as Usual, April 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Actions -- Pentagon Blockade, October 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Actions -- War in the Persian Gulf Forum -- Northwestern University, November 1987
  - Audio Recording -- Tape 1 (Box 9, Folder 328.0018)
  - Audio Recording -- Tape 2 (Box 9, Folder 328.0019)
  - Fliers, Readings, and Talk Transcripts (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Actions -- Demonstrations at the 1988 Democratic National Convention -- Atlanta, July 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Actions -- No Holiday as Usual -- Songs, December 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Actions -- Ungreet the Fleet, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Actions -- Video Recording -- "U.S. Out" -- San Francisco Bay Demonstrations on Honduras, circa 1988-1989 (Box 8, Vhs 328.0005)
- Actions -- Unidentified Audio Recordings, undated
  - Side 1-2 (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.0012)
  - Side 3-4 (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.0009)
- Actions -- Unidentified Video Recording, undated (Box 8, Vhs 328.0004)
- Boston Committee, circa 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Brochure and Pledge, circa 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Budget, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Campus Action Planning Conference -- Brown University, February 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chicago Committee
  - Publicity, Mailings, and Photographs, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Video Recording -- Intervention and Global War: The Challenge to Respond -- A Forum, circa 1985 (Box 8, Vhs 328.0006)
- Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Fundraising, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Hawaii Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Mailing, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- National Mailings, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15, Box 3, Folder 1)
- National Mailings, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- National Mailings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
- National Mailings, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- National Mailings, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- National NBAU Conference, May 1988
  - Audio Recording -- Q and A Session 1 (Box 9, Folder 328.0013)
  - Audio Recording -- Q and A Session 2 (Box 9, Folder 328.0014)
  - Report (Box 3, Folder 8)
- National Organizing Committee, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- National Planning Conference for NBAU Day, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- National Response Committee, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- New York Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Newsletters, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Organizing Kit, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Other Organizations
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - A, 1984-1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - B, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Committee for Peace and Freedom in Iran, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - C, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - D, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - E, 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - F-G, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hands Off!, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Honeywell Project, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - I, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Jonah House, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - K-L, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mobilization for Survival, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - N, 1978-1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - O, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Peacemaker, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - P, 1980-1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - R, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Stop the U.S. War Machine Action Network, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - S, 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - T-V, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - War Resisters League, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 10-11, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - W, 1983-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Y, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Press Clippings, November 1984-February 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Press Clippings, April 1985 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
- Press Clippings, August 1985 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Press Clippings, April 1986 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Press Clippings, October 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
- Press Releases and Statements, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Press Releases and Statements, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Press Releases and Statements, 1987-1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Regional Conference -- Midwest -- Chicago, May-June 1986
  - Audio Recording -- Panel Discussions Master Recordings -- AM Panels -- Tape 1 (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.0011)
  - Audio Recording -- Panel Discussions Master Recordings -- AM Panels -- Tape 2 (Box 9, Audiocassette 328.0015)
  - Audio Recording -- Panel Discussions Master Recordings -- PM Panels (Box 8, Audiocassette 328.0007)
  - Audio Recording -- Star Wars: Preparation for World War Panel (Box 9, Audiocassette 328.0021)
  - Audio Recording -- Star Wars: Preparation for World War Panel Discussion (Box 9, Audiocassette 328.0022)
  - US Bombing of Libya Panel (Box 9, Audiocassette 328.0017)
  - US Bombing of Libya Panel (Box 9, Audiocassette 328.002)
  - Flyer and Program (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Regional Conference -- Western -- Berkeley, June 1986 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Speakers Bureau, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Subject Files
  - Discriminate Deterrence, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Kissinger, C. Clark -- "Don't Be a 'Good German' on November 6", November 1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Nuclear Weapons, 1981-1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Washington, D.C. Committee, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)